All right, חסל פורים, Chasal Purim, סוף סוף פורים שמח. sof sof
Purim Sameach. We pick up at the top of כ"ד עמוד א'.
Kaf-Daled Amud Aleph. Not working? Never mind. Okay. Anyway, top of כ"ד
עמוד א', Kaf-Daled Amud Aleph, אמר רב הושעיה, Amar Rav Hoshaiah, first
line. Okay, so we are dealing within the discussion about חטאת המתה,
Chatas HaMeisah, and we saw a debate of רבי Rebbi and the
רבנן Rabbanan about they both required that the thing first be lost
and then a question is whether it was found after you'd designated
the second one or after you'd brought the second one.
And then we introduced a position of רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, who
said חמש חטאות מתות, Chamesh Chataos Meisos, before he had said that
sort of categorically, meaning they all come as a group, though the
גמרא Gemara also read this to be an even more extreme position
than רבי, Rebbi, that he has very little nuance in terms of
that there would be ever any exceptions to the הלכה Halacha of
a חטאת המתה. Chatas HaMeisah. So let's take a look, and then
the גמרא Gemara had introduced the idea that if you have if
you designate two piles of money from the outset, even רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon would agree because then it is always true there was
always one for אחריות, achrayus, and even he would say that's not
a case of that you have to if you select one, the
other has to be destroyed. Let's now we're going to continue to
sort of discuss this idea of designating from the outset, except instead
of two piles of money, we're going to talk about two animals
from the outset. So, top of כ"ד עמוד א', Kaf-Daled Amud Aleph,
אמר רב הושעיה, Amar Rav Hoshaiah, המפריש שתי חטאות לאחריות. HaMafrish shtei
chataos l'achrayus.
So you designate not two piles of money from the outset, but
two different animals, both as a חטאת, Chatas, you sanctify both of
them, and it's a backup, one for the other, which is never
smart because you know that's just going to get you into trouble.
Just wait till you lose one, then you'll do the other one.
But
okay. Anyway, נתכפר באחת מהן, Nis-kaper b'achas mehen, so you bring one
as a
קרבן, korban, וחברתה רועה, v'chavirtah ro'ah, and the other one grazes. It's
not a חטאת המתה Chatas HaMeisah because as we've been seeing for
it to be a חטאת המתה, Chatas HaMeisah, it's not enough that
it's נתכפר באחר, nis-kaper b'acher, but you need it actually to have
been lost, and this was never lost, so it grazes. אליבא דמאן?
Aliba d'man? Yeah, אליבא דמאן? aliba d'man?
According to whom is this? אילימא אליבא דרבנן? Ileima aliba d'Rabbanan? Meaning
who do you have to tell me this? Who is this חידוש
chiddush according to? Isn't it pretty obvious? No. אילימא אליבא דרבנן? Ileima
aliba d'Rabbanan? Well, if it's according to the Rabbis, then it is
obvious. השתא המפריש לאיבוד, Hashta ha-mafrish l'ibud, אמרו רבנן לאו כאיבוד דמי.
amru Rabbanan lav k'ibud dami. Even when one is lost, when you
designate the other one to stand in for it, that's not enough
to give this other one a quasi-lost status, right? Remember that's how
the גמרא Gemara framed רבי's Rebbi's position, that it either had to
be lost or instead of one that was lost. But the Rabbis
aren't even, you know, if it's just instead of one that is
lost, that doesn't that's not enough for the Rabbis. So לאחריות מיבעיא?
L'achrayus mibaya? How much more so if it was from the very
outset there to be a backup and it there was never anyone
that was lost. How much more would that be a non-issue for
the Rabbis? Because the Rabbis need there to be something that was
lost. אלא אליבא דרבי שמעון? Ela aliba d'Rabbi Shimon? So it's leapfrogging
over רבי Rebbi because that's where it's going to end. So maybe
it's according to רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, דאמר רבי שמעון, d'amar Rabbi
Shimon, חמש חטאות מתות. chamesh chataos meisos.
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon said a while ago that five חטאות chataos
die. Now again, when he originally said that, the emphasis was it's
either all five or none. But here the גמרא Gemara is understanding
that to mean also like everything is categorical. So there's no exceptions
to the rules, meaning that he doesn't need there to be a
concept of it being lost, as long as the owner was toned
with another, this one dies. So he's even more extreme than רבי
מאיר. Rebbi Meir. So if that's true, then even then even in
this case, it would die. So the only case the גמרא Gemara
was willing to concede yesterday that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon would admit
is if you didn't actually have a חטאת Chatas that you designated
but a pile of money. Then you could say if you brought
one pile of money, the other one doesn't have to be destroyed.
But if you actually have two animals and one is brought and
it's נתכפר באחת, nis-kaper b'achas, then this one would be destroyed even
without a status of having been lost. He's more categorical, נתכפר באחר,
nis-kaper b'acher, at least if you're dealing with animals, you always kill
the other one.
So אלא אליבא דרבי. ela aliba d'Rebbi. It's according to רבי. Rebbi.
כי אמר רבי, Ki amar Rebbi, don't mistake רבי Rebbi for רבי
שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. רבי Rebbi is not categorical. When did רבי Rebbi
say that if you find it, you still the other one has
to die? That's באיבוד, b'ibud, when at least something was lost. So
even there was a status on lost on the lost one, or
there was a status on, you know, מפריש לאיבוד mafrish l'ibud corresponding
to the lost one on the other one. But you started with
a phenomenon of loss. If you build on the idea of loss,
then you have a חטאת המתה. Chatas HaMeisah. אבל אחריות לא, Aval
achrayus lo, if it's just there as a representing it, not. So
here the גמרא Gemara actually wait till he gets a מום, mum,
the money goes for נדבה. nedavah. So here the גמרא Gemara basically
has clarified, right? And it's important because normally you'd just say, oh,
נתכפר באחת, nis-kaper b'achas, and that's really what the גמרא Gemara in
the end says is just the outline שיטה shitta of רבי שמעון.
Rabbi Shimon. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says as long as you were
toned brought another for atonement, the other one dies regardless of circumstance.
But now we're finding that no, there actually according to רבי Rebbi
and the חכמים, Chachamim, there's a lot of nuance. Both רבי Rebbi
and the חכמים Chachamim require first of all that the idea that
you were toned brought another for atonement first builds on the fact
that one of them was lost and according to the
and therefore the one that was lost in addition to being lost
you brought an atonement for another or the one that was. opposite
the one that was lost, then you brought something else for an
atonement, but it starts with reality that something was lost and then
it builds on that. And then even within that, the חכמים Chachamim
say only after it was
atoned, and רבי Rebbi says even after you even after you sanctify
the other one. But even there the rabbis might agree with say
a bit distinction whether you're bringing number one or number two, but
there's a lot of distinctions and it starts with the idea according
to רבי Rebbi and the רבנן Rabbanan that you need something that
was lost. And only רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon says it's in all
cases, שנתכפר באחר היא מתה. she’nitkaper be’acher, hi mesa. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara goes on, says like this. אמר ר... Amar R...
okay, now let's take a look. תנן: Tnan: המפריש חטאת והרי היא
בעלת מום. Ha’mafrish chatas ve’harei hi ba’alas mum. So this is actually
our משנה Mishnah that we had a while that we had before.
Somebody designates a חטאת Chatas and it starts with a מום. mum.
Okay, this is the very end of the משנה Mishnah that started
our פרק perek or that was whatever the second משנה Mishnah of
the פרק, perek, the last משנה Mishnah that we had. המוכרה ומביא
אחר תחתיה. Hamochrah u’meivi acher tachteha.
You sell it, right? You redeem it and you bring something in
its stead. That's a simple case. That's just redeeming an animal with
a מום. mum. But then you get the extreme position of רבי
אלעזר ברבי שמעון. Rabbi Elazar b’Rebbi Shimon. רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון אומר
אם קרבה שניה קודם שנשחטה ראשונה, Rabbi Elazar b’Rebbi Shimon omer im
karva shniya kodem she’nishchata rishona, if you actually brought the קרבן Korban
before you שחט shechted the first one. The first one had been
redeemed, right? I had a מום. mum. What did I do with
this animal with a מום? mum? I sold it to Michael, he's
going to have steaks tonight. שבת Shabbos of steaks, whatever, pot roast.
Anyway, I go ahead and I'm bringing it as
a קרבן. Korban. If I bring my קרבן Korban before he actually
שחט shechted his animal, his animal gets defined as a חטאת שנתכפרו
בעליה באחר. Chatas she’nitkapru ba’aleha be’acher. And now he cannot, the fact
that it once was a חטאת Chatas it retains that identity still
so that it will be defined as that
and now he has to let it die. So the גמרא Gemara
says, it's a pretty extreme position, so who does that work according
to?
שמת, She’yamus, it has to die, שכבר נתכפרו בעליה she’kvar nitkapru ba’aleha
the owners were atoned with with number two. קסלקא דעתך Kasalka daiteich
רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון כרבי סבירא ליה. Rabbi Elazar b’Rebbi Shimon k’Rebbi
svara leh. We thought this was aligned with the position of רבי,
Rebbi, that needs it to be a, that רבי Rebbi in our
משנה Mishnah is the more מחמיר machmir one. He says that even
if it was the other one was found
before you שחט shechted number two. So we assume that he was
רבי, Rebbi, that it was a building on
רבי. Rebbi. ואפילו באחריות נמי לא? Ve’afilu ba’achrayus nami lo? And you
see even in the case of אחריות achrayus because in that case,
right, the animal had a מום, mum, it's not like there was
an animal even if you say, meaning it assumes two things. Number
one, it assumes the animal retains its identity as a חטאת Chatas
even after it's redeemed. Fine, let's grant you that point, it was
redeemed, it still retains its identity as a חטאת. Chatas. But it
was never lost, right? So it's not analogous to the normal case.
It's not that it was lost. So even if it retains its
identity, why is it a מתה mesa if it was never lost?
That could be perfectly like אחריות. achrayus. What's the law of אחריות?
achrayus? I have two here, I say because if I use in
case something happens to one, I'll use the other one. That's exactly
what happened here. This one couldn't be used, I used another one,
it was never lost, right? So it should never have, even if
רבי Rebbi requires the concept of loss, why is that מתה mesa
even if it retains its status as a חטאת? Chatas? So the
גמרא Gemara says, לא, Lo, no, it's not, he doesn't hold like
רבי. Rebbi. לא דאמר רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון כאבוה סבירא ליה. Lo,
de-Rabbi Elazar b’Rebbi Shimon k’avuhu svara leh.
He's the son of רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, maybe he holds like
his father רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. דאמר חמש חטאות מתות. D’amar chamesh
chattos mesos. Five חטאות chattos die regardless of circumstance,
so it doesn't need a quality of being lost. So as long
as you can say that even after it's redeemed it retains that
identity of חטאת, Chatas, then רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says it's always
מתה mesa if you're atoned with another and therefore that would be
מתה. mesa.
Why would we want to say that this does retain its status?
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara is going to get to that. But
the point is even if we concede that point, whatever happens to
the status of אבוד? avud? So the גמרא Gemara is now clearly
defining the parameters. Only רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says that שנתכפר באחר
nitkaper be’acher regardless of circumstance, both רבי Rebbi and the רבנן Rabbanan
require a concept of אבוד, avud, and the only debate is some
of the circumstances of that. What happens if it was אבוד בשעת
הפרשה לא בשעת הקרבה? avud b’shas hafrasha, lo b’shas hakrava? What about
if it was number one and not number two, and number two
and not number one, exactly where you define the qualities of אבוד?
avud? And if you want to remember what we even said a
few דפים dappim ago, what happens if in addition to being אבוד
avud it was also a case of עברה שנה, avras shnah, if
it had a מום? mum? So in certain so circumstances where there's
a lot of so-to-speak stigmas to it or ways it's been pushed
away, and you add שנתכפר באחר, nitkaper be’acher, then would they say
that it's מתה, mesa, but not in all cases. Okay, so it's
much more qualified than we normally assume.
Yes. How, what would be the practical cases of what we just
discussed? He buys your first one. Yeah. How is he going to,
yeah, is he going to, I mean, are you telling him that,
you better שחט shecht this before I bring my second?
I wish he'd probably do that, and if I didn't, whether he
has a responsibility to assume, what assumptions he can... make, right? The
גמרא Gemara isn't spelling that out. I mean that's like a separate
conversation, but you're right, that would be a conversation necessary to have,
you know, like the גמרא Gemara just discussed when we did well,
אותו ואת בנו, Oso V'Es Beno, when I sell the mother one
day and I sell the child on the same day, do I
have to inform a person who has the responsibility to know, to
find out, but I would assume minimally it's my responsibility to tell
him, anyway I would tell him because it limits his use of
it, that this used to be a קרבן Korban and, you know,
and now you by your giving me the money for it it's
transferring the קדושה Kedusha on it because anyway that means that he
can't graze it, he can't, you know, you know, he can't, I
mean work it, he can't shear it and so on. So he
does know it used to be a קרבן. Korban. I wonder if
I have to tell him it used to be a חטאת. Chatas.
Presumably I would, you know, or else how should he know? All
right, and he'd שחט Shecht it right away. And then he would
realize that he better שחט Shecht it before I, right, but yeah
exactly who has the responsibility, you know, to find out all the
details, I'm not clear. All right, so now the גמרא Gemara says
like this.
Okay, תנן, Tnan, לפי שאין חטאת ציבור מתה. Lefi She'ein Chatas Tzibbur
Mesa. So we're back to that famous משנה Mishnah we like quoting
in יומא Yoma that says that when you bring a substitute
pair because the שעיר לעזאזל Seir L'Azazel died, so you have to
bring another pair and then it says so what do you do
with the extra שעיר לחטאת, Seir L'Chatas, right, you understand your first
pair the שעיר לעזאזל Seir L'Azazel died, you had a remaining שעיר
לחטאת, Seir L'Chatas, then you bought another pair. Okay, so you're only
going to use the שעיר לעזאזל Seir L'Azazel from the other pair.
You're going to have one of them is going to be an
extra שעיר לחטאת. Seir L'Chatas. So it says let it graze because
a communal קרבן Korban never we never say תמות. Tamus. Okay, so
שאין חטאת ציבור מתה. She'ein Chatas Tzibbur Mesa. הא דיחיד Ha D'Yachid
מתה. Mesa. And we always now we're trying to figure out according
to which of the שעיר לחטאות Seir L'Chatas-es are you going to
bring? Number one or number
two? ואמר רב V'Amar Rav בעלי חיים אינם נדחים. Ba'alei Chaim Einan
Nidchin. Now we're working with רב's Rav's שיטה Shita that says that
the living animal was not pushed off. So the שעיר לחטאת Seir
L'Chatas of pair number one is going to be used, what was
fit was not rejected, there was nothing wrong with it, it's just
that its mate died. So therefore כשמכפר בשני שבזוג ראשון מכפר. Keshemiskhaper
B'Sheini Sheb'Zug Rishon Miskhaper. So you're going to bring your the שעיר
לחטאת Seir L'Chatas is going to be the second the one of
pair number one. So when you bring pair number two, one of
them will be your שעיר לעזאזל Seir L'Azazel and the other one,
the שעיר לחטאת Seir L'Chatas will be extra. And right, got it,
because you're going to use the first שעיר לחטאת. Seir L'Chatas. So
that שעיר לחטאת Seir L'Chatas that were extra, if it were because
ציבור Tzibbur doesn't die, but if it were יחיד Yachid it would
die. We asked how, we asked this already, but how we framed
what that one was is very different, which תוספות Tosafos asks. So
the גמרא Gemara says like this, how do we understand the quality
of that second שעיר? Seir? So the גמרא Gemara says like
this, ואידך הדרי אחריות. V'Idach Hadri Achrayus. That second שעיר Seir is
like a substitute, is like a backup. Now obviously you could say
why is it like a backup? You know from the very beginning
you're not going to use it, right? The whole idea of אחריות
Achrayus is I might use one I might use the other. So
the גמרא's Gemara's going to get to that, but for now somehow
it's saying like at least if אחריות Achrayus means it's not אבוד,
Avud, so okay, it's not אבוד. Avud. It doesn't have the quality
of being lost. One minute, so since it doesn't have the quality
of being lost and you said you needed the quality of being
lost, why are you saying that that would die were a similar
were an analogous case be by an individual? One minute, ותני דיחיד
מתה. V'Sani D'Yachid Mesa. It says implicitly if it were a case
of an individual, it would die. So why is it that the
second one of the pair when you bring a new pair, right,
would would die if it were similar if that were a case
by an individual since it never had the quality of אבוד, Avud,
it was never lost? And the גמרא Gemara says the גמרא's Gemara's
answer is probably what you could have expected, which in a way
we already said yesterday. רב לטעמיה, Rav L'Tameih, רב Rav with his
reasoning, it's the same רב Rav that we said בעלי חיים אינם
נדחים, Ba'alei Chaim Einan Nidchin, דאמר מצוה בראשון. D'Amar Mitzvah B'Rishon. Now
there's a מצוה Mitzvah to bring the first one. Not only is
it can you opt to bring the first one of the first
pair, you must bring the one of the first pair. And therefore
what? Therefore it means if you thought you could choose, meaning here's
clear what the גמרא's Gemara's question was. It thought you could choose
whether you're going to and which of those two animals you would
bring. If you could choose, it was like אחריות, Achrayus, you could
choose which one to bring. But says no no no, you know
from the outset you're only going to bring the remnant the second
one of the first pair and you know from the outset that
the second one of the second pair you're not going to use.
So that's basically like from the very beginning you're labeling it as
rejected. Therefore from the very beginning it has a status like אבוד.
Avud. It's equivalent to the idea of being lost because from the
very outset even you know that this second one cannot be used
and therefore it can be a status of נתכפר באחר. Niskaper B'Acher.
Now you'll remember yesterday when the גמרא Gemara introduced it, it actually
started from that point, that the second one is כיוון דאבוד דמי.
Keevan D'Avud Dami. Okay, so תוספות Tosafos points that out. He says
well you know maybe yesterday's גמרא Gemara was after the conclusion of
today's גמרא. Gemara. Okay, but yes, it's funny that here the גמרא
Gemara conceives of it one way and yesterday another way, but in
the end the answer is since you know you're not going to
use it from the very beginning, it's equivalent to the idea of
being lost and it has a status of נתכפר באחר. Niskaper B'Acher.
Yes.
Okay the שעיר לעזאזל Seir L'Azazel dies, you bring in the second
pair, you select the one that's going to be the replacement for
the dead one and then the one from the original pair that
was to be the חטאת Chatat dies.
What would you do then?
What would you do then? Would you bring another, a third pair?
Or would you actually use the?
Well, since, okay.
But no, and the reason I ask that is that, that's a
possibility of why it's called אחריות?
achrayut? Yes. Okay, well that's an interesting question.
I would think that since it's a חטאת ציבור, Chatat Tzibbur, it
never had a status of
מתה. meita. First of all, the מתה meita only occurs after הקרבה,
hakrava, right? Even Rebbe that says מתה meita is when you find
it before הקרבה hakrava says that it only gets labeled as מתה
meita once you're actually מקריב. makriv. So in your scenario where you
never מקריב, makriv, you would be able to use the second one.
So you're saying that it would only be a disputed question according
to Rabbi Shimon, Shimon then?
Yeah, or even according to him, I think nobody says that you
need the reality of נתכפר באחר. nitkaper b'acher. Before you actually bring
one of them, before you have נתכפר באחר, nitkaper b'acher, I don't
think the label is permanent because it's not yet נתכפר באחר. nitkaper
b'acher. So in your scenario, you'd be able to go back, you'd
be able to bring the second one of the second pair, which
is maybe why you could say it has a quasi-אחריות, achrayut, but
not really, because that's true in every scenario. If the other, if
one of them died, you'd be left, you'd be able to, it
requires the status of נתכפר באחר. nitkaper b'acher. Okay. All right, I
see everybody's on the ball today. Let's keep on going. So the
גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay. תני רב שימי בר זירא קמיה
דרב פפא. Tani Rav Shimi bar Zeira kamei d'Rav Papa. אבדה בשעת
הפרשה. Avda b'sha'at hafrasha.
Now here was an interesting ברייתא braita that seems to have not
been part of the entire previous conversation, but this was a ברייתא
braita that he had. Okay, so you'll be a little surprised at
this I think. Okay. אבדה בשעת הפרשה, Avda b'sha'at hafrasha, if it
was lost at the time of being separated, but meaning but found
before it was brought, so לרבי מתה, l'Rebbe meita, Rebbe it's going
to die anyway even if it was found before the other one
was brought. לרבנן תרעה, l'Rabbanan tir'eh, the Rabbis say as long as
it was found before the second one's brought, it only grazes and
proceeds go for an עולה. olah. Now how about if it was
the other case? אבדה בשעת כפרה, Avda b'sha'at kapara, if it was
lost when you actually brought number two and then you found it,
לרבנן מתה, l'Rabbanan meita, for the Rabbis they would say that it
dies because then it was really נתכפר באחר, nitkaper b'acher, it was
only found after you brought number two. And then his ברייתא braita
says לרבי רועה, l'Rebbe ro'eh, but according to Rebbe it would graze,
it was that Rebbe and the Rabbis were the exact mirror image
of one another. So it wasn't that it was a continuum and
everybody agreed that when it was found later it was worse, but
actually no, Rebbe says that it was worse when it was found
earlier, it was better when it was found later. Now to some
degree you could understand the logic of this, right? Because when it
was found earlier and I select number two over number one, I
am like pushing away number one. I have the option of using
number one and I'm rejecting it. Whereas if it was found after
I brought number two, I didn't actively reject number one, I just
didn't know that it was around, I didn't have it available, so
maybe it's not as bad. So he actually had a version that
Rebbe and the Rabbis, it wasn't that you know earlier and later
was clearly better or worse, they actually debated it and they were
mirror images of one another. Anyway, this is what he taught in
front of.
My notion when נתכפר nitkaper would be.
Well, both well, it's always נתכפר באחר, nitkaper b'acher, but it's not
always מתה. meita. We've said it requires certain other qualities to be
מתה. meita. It requires אבדה avda and so on, so maybe one
of the qualities is if you hear like, you know,
חטאת...
ומתה, Chatat... u'meita, the one נתכפר באחר nitkaper b'acher wouldn't have.
All right, fine. Anyway, you wouldn't fight to make these distinctions either.
Anyway, Rav Papa didn't like it. So here's what Rav Papa said
back then. He said קל וחומר, kal v'chomer, no, what are you
talking about? It's so even you know, it's even more so. ומה
אבודה בשעת הפרשה דאמרי רבנן רועה אמר רבי מתה, u'mah avuda b'sha'at
hafrasha d'amri Rabbanan ro'eh amar Rebbe meita, if when it was lost
only at the time of sanctifying the second one, I mean it
was found earlier, here's where
the Rabbis say graze and Rebbe says die. So Rebbe is so
מחמיר machmir to say die even when it was found earlier. אבודה
בשעת כפרה, avuda b'sha'at kapara, so when it was found later and
it was lost even at a later
stage, it was lost even when it was atoned and it was
only found after you brought number two, לרבנן מתה, l'Rabbanan meita, the
Rabbis would say it dies, לרבי לא כל שכן, l'Rebbe lo kol
sheken, how much more so should Rebbe agree? If even the Rabbis
say it dies, there all the more so should Rebbe agree. So
he sees it as a straight continuum. Earlier is better than later,
and if it was found later, how much more so is it
נתכפר באחר nitkaper b'acher and therefore obviously Rebbe should agree.
אלא תני הכי, Ela tani hachi, change your text, have your ברייתא
braita say the following. אבודה בשעת הפרשה לרבי מתה לרבנן רועה, Avuda
b'sha'at hafrasha l'Rebbe meita l'Rabbanan ro'eh, if it was only lost and
then found whatever before the second one was brought, then Rebbe says
die and the Rabbis say graze. בשעת כפרה, B'sha'at kapara, if it
was even lost when the second one was brought and only found
later, דברי הכל מתה, divrei hakol meita, then everybody would say it
dies. That it's clearly an issue of a continuum, it's not an
issue of picking one as worse than the other. But actually that
was an interesting ברייתא braita that Rav Papa didn't like and it
was against everything we've been saying, but actually suggested there's ways of
thinking that בשעת הפרשה b'sha'at hafrasha is worse than בשעת כפרה. b'sha'at
kapara. Okay, now we wrap up with the very surprising position of
רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rabbi Elazar b'Rebbe Shimon that we quoted before
that says that even after you've redeemed it, it retains the status
of a חטאת, chatas, so that if the other קרבן korban is
brought first, this one has to die even after it's been redeemed.
Let's take a look. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. אין מראגלין ביום טוב.
Ein maraglin b'Yom Tov. You cannot do the removal of the skin
from the legs on יום טוב. Yom Tov. They would remove, they
would flay off the skin from an animal in order to use
it for leather. Now apparently the easy way to do it would
be to cut it down lengthwise down the stomach of the animal
and to pull it off like that, but then it would not
be as usable for flasks or whatnot because you would not have
a whole as large of a piece as an uncut, you know,
piece of leather. So the way to do it, the more difficult
way, but the way that made better use of it, was to
somehow pull it off from the legs up. I'm not exactly sure
how, don't ask me, but anyway, it was a more difficult way,
but it made better use of the leather. You cannot do this
on יום טוב. Yom Tov. On יום טוב, Yom Tov, you can
שחט, shecht, but don't remove the leather this way on יום טוב.
Yom Tov.
Wait, so are we talking about everybody?
Yeah, it has nothing to do with a קרבן. korban. Yeah, you
שחט shecht a cow in your backyard for steaks on יום טוב.
Yom Tov. Okay? Don't remove the leather, the skin this way.
And you couldn't even do that in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash
either, right?
Right, right, because it's not a צורך יום טוב. tzorech Yom Tov.
שחיטה shechita is צורך יום טוב, tzorech Yom Tov, but this is
an unnecessary טירחא tircha on יום טוב. Yom Tov. You're not going
to use the leather on יום טוב. Yom Tov. Okay. כיוצא בו,
kayotzei bo, אין מראגלין בבכור ולא בפסולי המוקדשין. ein maraglin b'bechor velo
b'psulei hamukdashin.
Similarly,
if you have a בכור bechor or an animal that has a
מום, mum, a קרבן korban that has a מום mum that you
redeemed, so you cannot do this as well to these animals. Now
we'll see why not in a minute. Let's take a look. The
גמרא Gemara is going to ask why all this is true. בשלמא
ביום טוב, bishlama b'Yom Tov, I understand why you can't do it
on יום טוב, Yom Tov, דקא טרח טירחא דלא חזי ליה, d'ka
tarach tircha d'la chazi lei, because you're doing an effort that it's
not fit for you today, meaning you're expending a lot of effort
on יום טוב Yom Tov and there's not going to be no
יום טוב Yom Tov benefit, although you know you just want a
better piece of leather for after יום טוב. Yom Tov. אלא בכור
מאן תנא, ela bechor man tana, what's the reason that בכור, bechor,
we're assuming he means a בכור bechor with a מום. mum.
But if it was without a מום, mum, then the obvious reason
would be because the meat has
קדושה kedusha and therefore you know, and this is sort of, whatever,
it's like disrespectful to the rest of the animal which is going
to be eaten to be you know doing this type of a
process. But we're assuming here that we're talking with a בכור bechor
with a blemish. So why is that a problem?
מאן תנא? man tana? So אמר רב חסדא בית שמאי היא. amar
Rav Chisda Beis Shammai hi. It's בית שמאי Beis Shammai that says
even when it has a blemish, it still retains its קדושה. kedusha.
Now everybody agrees it retains קדושה kedusha with a blemish in the
sense that you can't graze it, you can't shear it, you can't
work it. But בית שמאי Beis Shammai says that it really has
almost the same level of קדושה kedusha that it had before. What
does this mean? How do we see this?
דתנן, d'tenan, בית שמאי אומרים, Beis Shammai omrim, לא ימנה ישראל עם
הכהן על הבכור, lo yimaneh Yisrael im hakohen al habechor, that when
a בכור bechor is brought as a קרבן, korban, it can only
be eaten by כהנים, Kohanim, it's like תרומה, terumah, they're their household.
What if it's not brought as a קרבן? korban? What if it
has a blemish? So that's a debate of בית שמאי Beis Shammai
and בית הלל. Beis Hillel. בית הלל Beis Hillel says, oh, it
has a blemish, so you only have some הלכות, halachos, don't you
know, don't shear it, don't work it, but basically anybody can eat
from the meat. ובית שמאי אומרים, u'Veis Shammai omrim, no, it's still
like the meat of a בכור. bechor. If it's still like the
meat of a בכור, bechor, only כהנים Kohanim can eat from it.
Okay? So according to בית שמאי Beis Shammai that says even after
the blemish it still is like the meat of a בכור, bechor,
so he's going to say,
you know, the emphasis with is the קדושה kedusha of the meat,
so you want to be emphasizing the meat and not be doing
this whole you know thing about pulling off the leather, whatever, which
obviously you know the meat is involved but it's not going to
be the focus of your activities, it's not respectful. The גמרא Gemara
says, רש"י Rashi says he has a phrase of נראה כעבודה בקדשים.
nirah k'avodah b'kodashim. I'm not exactly sure why it's like עבודה avodah
since what you're doing is, you know, after the animal has died.
So I don't know, to me it makes more sense that it's
just not respectful because if you're doing the business, and the גמרא
Gemara is actually going to say that it physically injures the meat,
but even if you don't say that, to me it seems if
your business is to focus on the leather, then you're disregarding the
meat when you're focusing on the leather and it's not respectful if
the meat is really what has the קדושה. kedusha.
And the meat you should not really do that as a עבודה
avodah in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash either.
No, no, you never did this in the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash.
The only הוה אמינא hava amina was that you could take off
the skin if it's a if it's פסולי המוקדשין. psulei hamukdashin. You
would never do this with a קרבן. korban. Well they take an
עולה. olah. Yeah, you skin it, but you don't skin it in
this skin from the legs.
No, no, this you would certainly not do by a קרבן. korban.
The question is would you do this when it has a מום.
mum. So it's בית שמאי Beis Shammai that says you don't do
it with, so if you stay you don't do it by בכור,
bechor, that's בית שמאי Beis Shammai that says that a בכור bechor
even with a מום mum is like it has the same קדושה.
kedusha. It's taken for granted that you don't do it by a
קרבן. korban.
But you can do it with your שלמים? shlamim?
Yeah, because it's disrespectful for the meat, I mean, the way רש"י
Rashi puts it, נראה כעבודה בקדשים nirah k'avodah b'kodashim which I don't
fully understand, but minimally it's disrespectful to the meat. So בית שמאי
Beis Shammai says that you don't do it if it's got a,
you don't do, so this that you don't do by בכור, bechor,
even a בכור bechor even if it has a מום, mum, is
בית שמאי Beis Shammai that says that it has the same קדושה.
kedusha. Okay, now how about פסולי המוקדשין? psulei hamukdashin? Let's say it's
a קרבן korban that's been redeemed. Now that's even less than a
בכור, bechor, right? Because a בכור bechor the קדושה kedusha remains on
it, I mean, whatever, it gets lowered or impacted or whatever, but
you can eat it without bringing it, but a קרבן korban with
a מום mum you redeem. the קדושה. Kedusha. So why would it
be that you cannot do this if it's been a redeemed קרבן?
Korban? So מאן תנא? Man Tana? אמר רב חסדא Amar Rav Chisda
רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rebbe Elazar b'Rebbe Shimon היא. hi. Ah, it's
רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rebbe Elazar b'Rebbe Shimon of our משנה Mishnah
that even after something has been redeemed it still retains its identity.
דתניא Detanya היו לפניו שתי חטאות. Hayu lifanav shtei chatos. Now he's
quoting a משנה. Mishnah. If you had two חטאות—excuse Chatos me, not
our משנה, Mishnah, it's a ברייתא Braisa actually that goes further than
our משנה. Mishnah. If you had two sin offerings. אחת תמימה ואחת
בעלת מום. Achas temima ve'achas ba'alas mum.
One blemished and the other unblemished. And they were both sanctified for
the same sin. It's not for two separate sins, so you're only
going to bring one and you're not going to use the other.
So תמימה תקרב, Temima tikarev, the unblemished one you bring as a
קרבן. Korban. בעלת מום תפדה, Ba'alas mum tipadeh, the one with the
blemish you redeem and then you'll use the money for an עולה.
Olah. נשחטה בעלת מום Nishchata ba'alas mum עד שלא נזרק דמה של
תמימה. ad shelo nizrak dama shel temima.
If you had shechted the one with the blemish before you had
thrown the blood of the unblemished, then מותרת. mutteres. Then you can
eat it. משינזרק דמה של תמימה אסורה. Mishenizrak dama shel temima assura.
Once, however, the second one was brought, then the first one becomes
forbidden. Now that was even the חכמים. Chachamim. That wasn't yet רבי
אלעזר ברבי שמעון. Rebbe Elazar b'Rebbe Shimon. רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון אומר
Rebbe Elazar b'Rebbe Shimon omer אפילו בשר בעלת מום בקדירה. afillu basar
ba'alas mum be'kdeira. Even if you've got it cooking in your pot,
in your cholent pot, the one that was redeemed,
ונזרק דמה של תמימה venizrak dama shel temima and the second one
was brought, it defines the first one as
נתכפרו בעליה באחר nitkapru be'aleha be'acher and יוצא לבית השרפה. yotzei leveit
hasereifa. Go ahead and burn it. Okay, now תוספות Tosafos points out
that this is more extreme than our משנה, Mishnah, right? In our
משנה Mishnah it was only before you had shechted. Here even the
חכמים Chachamim say before you have shechted and רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון
Rebbe Elazar b'Rebbe Shimon says even if it's in the pot. So
תוספות Tosafos says the reason this is different is in our משנה,
Mishnah, first it got a מום, Mum, I redeemed it and transferred
it to another animal. That more fully removed the identity from the
first one as the חטאת Chatas because I basically
transferred the קדושה Kedusha to another one. Whereas in this case where
you started with both of them from the outset, right, the fact
that the first one is harder to lose its identity because from
the very beginning nothing is taken, you know, it wasn't that something
took its stead, there was already two from the very beginning, so
the first one doesn't lose its identity as quickly and therefore even
the rabbis would partially agree and רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rebbe Elazar
b'Rebbe Shimon would go so far to say even it was in
the pot.
Does that apply to the rest of the food too?
I assume so, sure. It's נותן טעם. nosein ta'am. Anyway, what you
see is that he says that it retains its identity even after
it's redeemed. So therefore, where were we? Okay. רב חסדא Rav Chisda
לוקמא אליבא דבית שמאי. lukma aliba de'Beis Shammai. Okay, so now we
have it. So we have בית שמאי Beis Shammai says a בכור
Bechor retains its קדושה Kedusha after it's redeemed. And רבי אלעזר ברבי
שמעון Rebbe Elazar b'Rebbe Shimon says—now obviously he says you're allowed to
eat the meat, but it's still the way he would frame it
is that the same way בית שמאי Beis Shammai says you can
eat the meat of a בכור Bechor without bringing it as a
קרבן. Korban. Fine. But it's a special היתר. heter. Although בית שמאי
Beis Shammai would say this is exactly like the קדושת בכור kedushas
Bechor because it has a מום Mum you're allowed to eat it
without bringing it as a קרבן. Korban. But fundamentally it's the same
קדושה. Kedusha. And it sounds like the גמרא Gemara is saying very
similar to רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון. Rebbe Elazar b'Rebbe Shimon. What you're
allowed to do with it is a היתר, heter, but fundamentally it's
the same קדושה Kedusha and it still has the identity of a
חטאת. Chatas. And therefore it could become a חטאת שנתכפרו בעליה באחר.
Chatas she'nitkapru be'aleha be'acher. And therefore if you had a prohibition of
removing, like the issue of removing the skin, that would continue to
apply here because this has the same קדושה Kedusha of a חטאת.
Chatas.
Wait, so what's the difference between בית שמאי Beis Shammai and רבי
אלעזר ברבי שמעון? Rebbe Elazar b'Rebbe Shimon?
So that's what the גמרא Gemara is going to say. Why are
you presenting them as different positions? One said by בכור, Bechor, one
said by פסולי המוקדשים. Pesulei Hamukdashim. And now the גמרא Gemara is
going to say you cannot necessarily assume that they would agree with
one another. So let's take a look.
ורב חסדא לוקמא אידי ואידי כבית שמאי. Ve'Rav Chisda lukma idi ve'idi
ke'Beis Shammai. Why not just say בית שמאי Beis Shammai applies to
both cases? Take what בית שמאי Beis Shammai says by בכור Bechor
and apply it to the other one. No. דילמא כי קאמרי בית
שמאי בבכור? Dilma ki ka'amri Beis Shammai be'bechor?
Maybe when did they say it retains its קדושה Kedusha by
בכור? Bechor? דקדושתיה מרחם, Dekedushtei merachem, it's sanctified automatically. But when it's
born. אבל פסולי המוקדשים לא, Aval Pesulei Hamukdashim lo, but they wouldn't
say it by פסולי המוקדשים. Pesulei Hamukdashim. Now the answer is it's
not just that its קדושה Kedusha comes automatically, it's also that you
don't redeem a בכור. Bechor. So if anything, right, it makes sense
by a בכור Bechor to say that even with the מום Mum
it much more holds onto its קדושה Kedusha whereas פסולי המוקדשים Pesulei
Hamukdashim you've redeemed it. So you would see more logically it doesn't
have as much of the קדושה. Kedusha. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara says ולוקמא אידי ואידי כרבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון. Velukma idi ve'idi
ke'Rebbe Elazar b'Rebbe Shimon. So okay, but if רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון
Rebbe Elazar b'Rebbe Shimon says by even after you've redeemed a קרבן
Korban it retains its identity, let him say it by other things.
No. דילמא כי אמר רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון בפסולי המוקדשים דאלימי למיתפס
פדיון? Dilma ki amar Rebbe Elazar b'Rebbe Shimon be'Pesulei Hamukdashim de'alimei le'mitfas
pidyon? No, maybe this idea of retaining its identity is more by
other קרבנות. Korbanos. Why? Because they have these so strong that the
money, when you can transfer their קדושה Kedusha to money—like by בכור
Bechor you can't transfer its קדושה Kedusha to money; by קרבנות Korbanos
with a מום Mum you can. So that means conceptually it's like
the קדושה Kedusha is stronger because it's able to grab other things.
So if it has a stronger קדושה, Kedusha, maybe even more of
it is retained after the fact.
אבל בבכור לא. Aval be'bechor lo. If a בכור's Bechor קדושה's Kedusha
not strong enough to attach to other things, maybe it's not as
much retained after it gets a מום. Mum. Okay, so there we
at least have two fascinating positions which very nicely the גמרא Gemara
to bring them together that even though these things with a מום
Mum you're allowed to eat them out of the
בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Now the
גמרא Gemara asks one final question. What about by a
חטאת, Chatas, right?
Well, the גמרא Gemara says generically פסולי המוקדשין, pesulei hamukdashim, so it
seems that רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון'ס Rabbi Elazar bar Rebbe Shimon's position
would be across the board, although the most extreme expression of it
would be by חטאת Chatas because it would transform it into a
חטאת שנתכפרו בעליה באחר. Chatas sheniscapru ba'aleha be'acher.
But the גמרא Gemara understands that his position would be across the
board by פסולי המוקדשין.
pesulei hamukdashim. Okay, so if a שלמים shelamim and had a מום
mum and then I did another one,
then there's no הלכה halacha of נתכפרו באחר niscapru be'acher by a
שלמים. shelamim. Right. So the conceptual thing he says by all קרבנות
korbanos that it retains its identity. What's the נפקא מינה nafka mina
by other קרבנות? korbanos? It's just about this thing of removing the
leather. By חטאת, Chatas, it's a more significant נפקא מינה. nafka mina.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
just wants to stay away from anyone who had חטאת. Chatas.
Well, yes,
according to רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון. Rabbi Elazar bar Rebbe Shimon. רבי
אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rabbi Elazar bar Rebbe Shimon לית ליה הא דתנן?
lais lei ha detnan? I don't get it, says the גמרא. Gemara.
What about the fact that we do know we allow you to
do certain things by פסולי המוקדשין pesulei hamukdashim that are not so
respectful in order so that you'll get a better price in the
market from them? And why do we want you to get a
better market price? Because since you're going to redeem them on the
value that they're worth, the value that they're worth is a function
of what you're going to be able to sell it for. And
therefore we give you greater latitude in terms of how you can
sell it, even slightly disrespectful ways, in order that it'll up the
price. What does the משנה Mishna say?
כל פסולי המוקדשין נשחטין באטליז, kol pesulei hamukdashim nishchatin be'itliz, they can
be slaughtered in the meat market, ונמכרין באטליז, venimkarin be'itliz, and sold
in the meat market, ונשקלין בליטרא, venishkalin belitra, and weighed out by
the pound. Right, it's treating them pretty much just like hunks of
meat. It's not so much acknowledging their previous קדושה kedushah status. But
we allow this in order to get a higher redemption price. אלמה
כיון דשרי ליה, alma keivan deshrei lei, if you're going to give
him this latitude, טפי וזבין, tefei vezavin, he will add to the
value and sell it at a higher price. So let's also allow
him to remove the skin in order to do that because if
at the end of the day we say that it is, I
mean, presumably you can frame it in two ways. You can say,
yes, it is a בזיון קדשים, bizayon kodashim, but we allow it
to get a higher price. Then you could say, oh, רבי אלעזר
ברבי שמעון, Rabbi Elazar bar Rebbe Shimon, maybe he doesn't agree, maybe
he holds that it's considered a higher level of קדושה kedushah and
he wouldn't allow it. But it seems like the גמרא Gemara is
implicitly assuming ultimately if it's for the best of the קרבן korban
and the best of the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, then in that
context it's not seen as inappropriate. So if that's true, why not
also allow the removing of the skin since it'll produce a better
price? Since you're going to use that money to get another קרבן,
korban, because the amount that you'll be able to sell it for
will be will determine how much you'll redeem it for. So
אמר מרי בריה דרב כהנא, amar Mari breih deRav Kahana, מה שמשביח
בעור פוגם בבשר. ma shemashbiach ba'or pogem babasar. No, you really don't
get a net benefit by removing the skin this way. Because however
much you benefit in the value of the leather, you're going to
lose out in the value of the meat because you're going to
have to mistreat the meat, which was part of the whole problem,
cut into the meat because you don't want to cut the leather.
And therefore the meat will be either, well, whatever you gain in
the sale value of the leather you'll lose in the sale value
of the meat, which would then you'd wonder why you'd bother doing
it. But who knows, maybe you could sell the leather quicker than
you could sell the meat or other
factors. Anyway, ומערבא משמיה דרב אבין, uMa'arava mishmeih deRav Avin, so they
gave a different answer in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael in the name
of רב אבין, Rav Avin, מפני שנראה כעובד עבודה בקדשים. mipnei shenireh
ke'oved avodah bekodashim. This is worse. Somehow when you're skinning the leather,
it looks like doing an עבודה בקדשים. avodah bekodashim. Before I said
רש"י Rashi I made a mistake, I meant the גמרא Gemara later,
I transposed it earlier. Anyway, it looks like you're doing an עבודה
בקדשים avodah bekodashim and that's worse than just the slight disrespect of
selling it in the marketplace. Now why skinning it looks like עבודה
בקדשים, avodah bekodashim, I don't know. רש"י Rashi says, and I'm trying
to remember one, it might have been you, Charlie, somebody explained this
I think last time we did this. רש"י Rashi says something about
blowing up, about
מפוח, mapuach, שעושה מפוח על בהמה בעודה מחוברת. she'oseh mapuach al behemah
be'odah mechuberes. Somehow that you would blow through it to sort of
do some you'd do some blowing into it to, I didn't exactly
get it, in order to remove the skin. Somebody said something about
knowing what he's talking about last time we did this.
Maybe it's easier to remove the skin. Yeah, separate from the meat.
I know, something like that. Anyway, somehow the way of doing this
is more than just disrespect, it seems somehow like you're making, you
know, you're doing עבודה avodah with it, which is hard to understand
how it can seem like עבודה avodah after it's dead. And let's
just read the
last answer. רב יוסי ברבי אבין אמר, Rav Yose bar Rebbe Avin
amar, גזירה שמא יגדל עדרים עדרים. gezeirah shema yigadel adarim adarim. No,
we get back to that problem, which is is that presumably the
גמרא Gemara understands that there's always a ready meat market, there's not
always a ready skin leather market. So if you want to use
it for the leather, you are going to maybe wait in order
to שחט shecht it, because you don't want to שחט shecht presumably
the leather goes bad or you want to sell it if you're
a wholesaler you're going to sell it to people that are going
to tan the leather. So obviously leather doesn't go bad, but you
have to tan it. So anyway, that market wasn't as predictable as
regular as the meat market, so you'll wait in order to do
that and then it'll lead to having babies and whatever, that'll increase
the price. So for whatever reason, the leather issue is a bigger
issue than selling it in the meat market, and the גמרא Gemara
while the גמרא Gemara could have framed that as a problem that
everybody agrees to for all those reasons, said you don't need רבי
אלעזר בר שמעון's Rabbi Elazar bar Shimon explanation. Right, it could just
be that those are sensitive issues of disrespect of something that used
to be a קרבן, Korban, but nevertheless at least initially, not clear
from the מסקנא, maskana, the גמרא Gemara said that that's connected to
רבי אלעזר בר שמעון Rabbi Elazar bar Shimon that it retains its
identity even after it's been redeemed. Yes, Charlie. How about the
meat?
Yes, so we bring שלמים Shlamim on יום טוב. Yom Tov.
Yes, we do.
And they have to be eaten either that day, that night, or
the next day. Right. So let's say יום טוב Yom Tov falls
on Friday,
you have to take the hide off so you can eat all
the meat. And you have to eat all the meat. Right, because
if you don't intend to eat all the meat, that's פיגול. pigul.
Well, no, פיגול pigul is only if you specifically intend to eat
it later, but anyway, but there's a לאו lav of לא תותירו
עד בוקר. lo totiru ad boker.
Okay,
well, I mean, the problem is you have to be careful to
take the hide off so you can get all the meat.
Yes, take the hide off, just take it the normal way. Don't
take it off from the legs, which is a very complicated process
and it's whatever, not as respectful to the meat, just slit it
down the
easy
way that doesn't, you don't, yeah.
And that preserves the meat better.
Yeah, exactly, yeah, yeah, definitely take the hide off.
Having never seen a slaughterhouse, I don't know.
Right, same here. All right, new פרק. perek. That is the end
to חטאת המתות. chatas hameisos. And although that was hard, that's the
end of חטאת. chatas. All those ולד vlad and תמורה tmura of
other animals and then the last פרק, perek, חטאת המתות. chatas hameisos.
Reminds me a little of יבמות Yevamos with all the different, right.
Now we get on to something, a great name of a פרק.
perek. כיצד מערימין. Keitzad marimin. How do you scheme?
Okay, כיצד מערימין על הבכור. Keitzad marimin al habechor. How do you
scheme regarding a בכור? bechor? Now, what's this mean? This is actually,
the גמרא Gemara will get into ways that would be the scheme
that gets you completely out of the application. Here the גמרא Gemara
is saying, no, no, no, you're not, you're not really trying to
fully get out of the application, but you figure, why give it
to the כהן? Kohen? If I'm going to have, if I'm not
going to be able to keep this baby that's born, I might
as well bring it as a קרבן Korban myself. So you're not
trying to completely get out and just keep it for your own
selfishness. You want to bring it as a קרבן, Korban, but why
should the כהן? Kohen? Let it be my קרבן. Korban. So what
are you going to do?
מבכרת שהיתה מעוברת. Mevakeres shehoyso muveres. You had a מבכרת, mevakeres, meaning
an animal that is going to give birth to its first child,
and it was pregnant. אומר, Omer, so you say: מה שבבטנה של
זו, mah shebibitna shel zo, אם זכר, im zachar, עולה. ola. What
the fetus in this, in the, in the womb of this
cow, if it is a male, let it be an עולה. ola.
And then if it's a female, it's nothing and that's good, you
can use it for yourself. If it's a male, rather than going
to have been a בכור bechor for a כהן, Kohen, you get
to bring it as your own עולה. ola. ילדה זכר יקרב עולה.
Yolda zachar yikarev ola. If it gives birth to a male, you
get to bring it as an עולה. ola. Okay, as your own
עולה, ola, you don't give it to a כהן. Kohen. Why? Because
בכור bechor doesn't apply to an animal if the mother or the
child is sanctified, and here the child is sanctified, and this assumes
that you can sanctify a fetus in the mother's womb, right, we
had that before, and it assumes that a בכור, bechor, which does
not become, does not have its קדושה, kedusha, which is not just
assumes, it's agreed, a בכור bechor does not get its קדושה kedusha
until the animal is born. So the sanctification of this fetus preceded
its status as בכור. bechor. Therefore, it's not a בכור, bechor, it's
an עולה, ola, you bring it as an עולה. ola. Yes.
But you don't get benefit from an עולה? ola?
No, but let's say anyway you had a חיוב chiyuv to bring
an עולה, ola, let's say anyway you just wanted to, you know,
bring your own קרבן Korban rather than give it to a כהן.
Kohen. Okay, but wait, it could be that you had a חיוב
chiyuv to bring an עולה. ola. If it
sounds like it, okay.
So what about the whole thing of like subverting almost?
Yeah, that's an interesting question. We'll talk about that. The גמרא Gemara
gets even more than that, so let's keep on going for a
while.
There's even more problem, right, because he gives it on בכורות. Bechoros.
Right. So now it says, and now let's say for some bizarre
reason, although that would be sufficient to get you out of בכור
bechor because the only case would be בכור bechor would be a
male, but let's say you decided to say, ואם נקבה תהא שלמים.
ve-im nekeiva t'hee shelamim. If it's a female, it'll be a שלמים.
shelamim. What's motivating you? The גמרא Gemara will discuss what might be
motivating you. But that's what you said. ילדה נקבה תקרב שלמים. Yolda
nekeiva tikarev shelamim. So then, of course, if that's what you stipulated,
it gave birth to a female, then it's a שלמים. shelamim.
What do I need to
be told something like that for? I don't know. We'll see in
the גמרא; Gemara; the גמרא Gemara is going to reframe it a
little bit.
אם זכר עולה ואם נקבה שלמים. Im zachar ola ve-im nekeiva shelamim.
If it's a male, it'll be an עולה, ola, if it's a
female, let it be a שלמים, shelamim, and again, we don't know
why you're bothering with the שלמים shelamim thing. Then, ילדה זכר ונקבה.
yolda zachar u'nekeiva. Let's say it's both a male and a female.
Then we could have said, well, which one is going to take
effect? But no, it says both of your conditions were met. It
was a male and it was a female. They were both met.
So they both become קרבנות. korbanos. הזכר יקרב עולה והנקבה תקרב שלמים.
Hazachar yikarev ola ve-hanekeiva tikarev shelamim.
So the male is an עולה, ola, the female is a שלמים.
shelamim. We don't say you meant only one. You said if a
male this and a female that, both were true, so both קדושות
kedushos took effect. Now, how about ילדה שני זכרים? yolda shnei zcharim?
Let's say it had twins and they were both male. So you
said if it's a male, let it be an עולה, ola, and
you only said it in the singular. So you're only going to
have one עולה ola here. Which one? You didn't say the first
one. You said it. So which one? So it says אחד מהם
יקרב עולה. echad meihem yikarev ola. let one of them be an
עולה, olah, because only one you sanctified, והשני ימכר לחייבי עולה ודמיו
חולין. ve-hasheni yimmakher le-chayyavei olah ve-damav chullin. The second one sell to
somebody who wants to have to bring an עולה. olah. Remember we
had this principle that once something was under the ambit of being
brought as a קרבן, korban, even if it never got the קדושה,
kedushah, we want to ensure it gets brought as a קרבן. korban.
So the second one I will sell to somebody that needs to
bring an עולה olah so eventually that will get brought as a
קרבן, korban, I mean under the understanding the person will bring it.
But because it didn't have קדושה, kedushah, the proceeds from that sale
I can pocket and keep.
And he can't come and say, like, oh, well you only meant
the second one
to be— So that's a good point. First of all, if we
get back to the—we're sort of ignoring the בכור bechor issue right
now. If we get back to the בכור bechor issue, then if
you choose the—first of all then you should be smart enough to
say if the first one is an עולה, olah, because anyway, if
there's one and the first one, whatever, because if it's a בכור
bechor and you know you only are treating the second one with
the קדושה, kedushah, then the first one should be a בכור. bechor.
That's question number one, what would happen in a בכור bechor case,
you know, presumably if you made the—if you chose the second, the
first one would be a בכור. bechor. But the real question is,
since when do you get to choose which one? Meaning how does
it work that you designate which one has the קדושה kedushah and
which one you sell? Maybe you say that it's implicit in your
condition, since your condition said one, implicitly there was some understanding that
if it wasn't clear you would get to choose which one. It's
not exactly clear how it gets to be your choice.
Wait, so wouldn't he have to know that there were two in
there before, right?
No, you didn't. That's why you said one, but there were—but if
it is male, let it be a בכור, bechor, קדושת עולה. kedushat
olah. There were two, so it's not clear which—so you only—you didn't
know there were two.
So if you—if you didn't know which it
was— Yes. —and the בכור bechor one as soon as it's born
gets the, of course, status as קדושה— kedushah Yes.
—and it's so—that was Michael's question. We should have probably by context
we should have assumed that the 'it' you meant is the first
one. And if there's a possibility you didn't mean the 'it' as
the first one, why don't you have to give the first one
to the כהן? kohen? Is that what you're asking?
Well I don't know, maybe I'm—I'm not sure that what I'm asking
is this. If you didn't know there were two, so how can
you say the first one?
How can you choose which one you meant?
No, how can you even say the first one if you didn't
know there were two coming out? There's no first. Oh right.
Oh you mean—oh you mean my point that you should stipulate. Right.
So you could say, you know, if there's only one let it
be a male, if there's more than one then the first one
is whatever. I mean you could sort of make your condition more
whatever. Okay, but the real question here is is that why do
you get to choose? Anyway, we'll talk about that, and what if
you chose the non-בכור, bechor, what would be the consequence? So we'll
see, we're not going to do it today. Okay. Now we go
on.
Now, let's
say ילדה שתי נקבות, yalda shetei nekeivot, it were two females, and
you said if it's a female let it, singular, be a שלמים.
shelamim. אחת מהן תקרב שלמים, achat me-hen tikarev shelamim, one of them
is a שלמים, shelamim, והשנייה תימכר לחייבי שלמים, ve-hasheniyah timmakher le-chayyavei shelamim,
the other one you sell to somebody who needs to bring a
שלמים, shelamim, by this principle,
once something is under the ambit of bringing a קרבן, korban, we
want to ensure it gets brought as a קרבן, korban, but it
never really had
קדושה, kedushah, ודמיה חולין, ve-dameha chullin, and the proceeds are חולין. chullin.
Okay, so those two are pretty much the same or are the
same הלכה. halachah. Again the question is how do you get to
choose which is which?
Now ילדה טומטום ואנדרוגינוס, yalda tumtum ve-androgynos, if we knew that was
coming to that, if you said male, female. Let's say it's a
טומטום, tumtum, which is an—which is the genitalia are covered up, אנדרוגינוס
androgynos it has both genitalia. So what do we say? רבן שמעון
בן גמליאל אומר אין קדושה חלה עליהם. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer
ein kedushah chalah aleihem. No, in that case they don't have any
קדושה, kedushah, not even מספק. mi-safek. Why—why is that true? אנדרוגינוס Androgynos
we could say is neither male nor female. But how about טומטום?
tumtum? So טומטום tumtum one possibility and we'll see how it gets
developed in the גמרא, Gemara, but the simplest possibility is you
meant זכר ודאי ונקבה ודאית, zachar vadai ve-nekeivah vadatait, you did not
mean to refer to a case where it was not able to
be determined even if in reality it was one or the other.
But we'll see how the גמרא Gemara discusses it. But anyway— Go
ahead.
We've—we've dealt with this before, haven't we?
Oh yeah. The גמרא—there Gemara are themes that are constantly—you mean the
whole status of טומטום tumtum and אנדרוגינוס? androgynos? Yeah, there are themes
that—that repeat themselves.
And he couldn't bring it as a קרבן korban anyway, a טומטום.
tumtum.
Yeah, but then you would have to פודה podeh it, redeem it,
whatever. Yeah, you couldn't bring it, but you'd have to, right, transfer
the value, and he says it's not קדוש kadosh at all. Okay,
אמר רב יהודה, amar Rav Yehudah, מותר להטיל מום בבכור קודם שיצא
לאוויר העולם. muttar le-hattil mum be-vechor kodem she-yatzah le-avir ha-olam. So first
we start with the idea of getting around בכור. bechor. And rather
than getting around with a—bringing a קרבן, korban, he says let's just
get out of the whole thing. I mean, not really the whole
thing, actually that would be even more radical. But actually what he
just says is before it actually is born, either stick your hand
in the womb or as the head is emerging, but before enough
of it has emerged to be considered born, make a—you know, cut
its lip, cut its ear, do something to make a מום. mum.
Okay, and therefore because it's not yet born, there is not yet
a prohibition, and then you won't have to bring it as a
קרבן, korban, and what will you do? You'll give it to the
כהן. kohen. According to him though, of course, the—you don't get yourself
a קרבן, korban, rather than the כהן kohen a קרבן, korban, what
you do is you make it easier for the כהן, kohen, but
in the end you're giving it to the כהן. kohen. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says תנן. tenan. So let's look at our
משנה: mishnah: אומר אדם מה שבמעי בהמה זו עולה. omer adam mah
she-bi-mei behemah zu olah. עולה אין שלמים לא. olah in shelamim lo.
In our משנה *Mishnah*, this gets to your question of, everybody's question
about, how can we subvert? The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says the only
scenario that the משנה *Mishnah* imagined allowing somebody to subvert was when
he sanctified it as an עולה olah. *Olah*. But you know what?
A שלמים shelamim, *Shelamim* not only can be a female, it could
be a male. So why didn't the משנה *Mishnah* give an example
that I sanctified and I said, if it's a male let it
be a שלמים shelamim *Shelamim*? Why did it only give the example
of עולה olah. *Olah*? So it says, presumably because it would not
be acceptable to say שלמים shelamim *Shelamim*. I mean, it would work,
but it wouldn't be appropriate. Why wouldn't it be appropriate? Because then
you're not getting making better use out of this fetus. If the
fetus would have been a בכור bechor. *Bechor*, the status would have
been the blood would have been on the altar and the כהן
kohen, *Kohein* would have eaten the meat. Now that you're making it
an עולה olah. *Olah*, it's all going on the altar. So that's
seen as a higher use. It's better. It's all going to God.
Now, if it were an עולה olah? *Olah*, it would all be
on the altar. If, however, that's why we're okay with you making
it an עולה olah. *Olah*, cause you're raising
its its status. But if you just made it a שלמים shelamim
*Shelamim*, שלמים shelamim. *Shelamim* is like a בכור bechor *Bechor*: the owners
eat the meat. So you're just, so you're not making it any
better. So we wouldn't have allowed it. So the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara*
says the reason in our משנה *Mishnah* we allowed this subversion was
because ultimately it raised the status of the בכור bechor *Bechor*. But
if it wouldn't do that, it was just שלמים shelamim. *Shelamim*, equivalent
status, or was like you making a מום mum, *Mum*, which got
it out of being on the altar, why should we allow such
a subversion?
So someone actually said, שלמים shelamim. *Shelamim* and what?
No, it would work, but would I get מלכות *Malkus*? No, but
it wouldn't be appropriate. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, why are
you saying that this is allowed, this is appropriate? Okay. שלמים ואת
אמרת דמטי
מפקי ליה מקדושתה *Shelamim v'at amarta demati mafkis lei mikedushatah*? And that's
to even give it an equivalent קדושה kedusha, *kedushah* we wouldn't allow.
You're saying that you could remove the קדושה kedusha. *kedushah*? Not literally
remove, but mean prevent it from being brought as a קרבן korban.
*Korban*. So אמר לך רב יהודה *amar lach Rav Yehudah*, so רב
יהודה *Rav Yehudah* will say back to you, one minute. It depends
what the context is. הני מילי בזמן שבית המקדש קיים *Hani mili
bizman sheBeis HaMikdash kayam*. The משנה *Mishnah* is talking in the theoretical
time when there's a בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash, *Beis HaMikdash*. If there's
a בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash. *Beis HaMikdash*, you have the possibility of
bringing it as a קרבן korban. *Korban*, so then the only thing
we would allow is if you could raise the status and turn
it into an עולה olah *Olah*. Equivalent שלמים *Shelamim* would not be
good. But that's cause it can really be a קרבן korban. *Korban*.
So therefore you cannot do worse with it. Okay.
The בכור bechor. *Bechor*, the blood goes but not the whole animal.
Exactly. And the meat is eaten by
the כהן kohen, *Kohein*.
The עולה olah *Olah*, the whole animal. The שלמים *Shelamim*, same as
the בכור Bechor *Bechor*. The blood is on the מזבח mizbe’ach *Mizbe'ach*
and the כהנים *Kohanim* eat and the owner eats the meat. Not
the כהן kohen. *Kohein*. Right. The only question is who eats the
meat. So says when there's a בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash *Beis HaMikdash*,
you're right. It would be a קרבן korban. *Korban*, and the only
change you could do would be to make it a better קרבן
*Korban*. Okay. כי קאמינא אנא *Ki kamina ana*, and when do I
say you can make a blemish? בזמן הזה *bizman hazeh*, nowadays. דלא
חזי לאקרבה *d'lo chazi l'akrava*. You can't bring it as a קרבן
*Korban*. So you can't bring it as a קרבן *Korban*, what's the
better function of this בכור bechor, *Bechor*? To stand around and do
nothing and die and wait till wait to because it'll never be
brought, for being a קרבן *Korban* it'll never be brought as? No,
the better thing is might as well make a מום mum *Mum*
now when it's still allowed, before it's been born, and then the
כהן kohen, *Kohein* can eat it right away and you won't run
into problems of misuse and the whole thing. So that's why I
allow it. I allow it because nothing is being lost by doing
this. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* said, one minute. And actually things
are being gained, there's won't be misuse. So the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara*
said, one minute. אי בזמן הזה מאי למימרא *E bizman hazeh mai
l'meimra*? If it's nowadays, of course, what you said is obvious. No,
מהו דתימא *mah d'teima*, it's not so obvious. Maybe I would think
נגזר דילמא נפיק רוב ראשו וקשדי ביה מומא *nigzar dilma nafik rov
rosho v'kashadi beimuma*. I might be afraid that when you're trying to
make a blemish before most of the head has come out, when
just the lips emerge, you'll be sloppy and you'll do it even
after the head has come down or the majority of the head
and then it'll be considered born and then there'll be a prohibition
to make a blemish. Wait, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says so
therefore I'm telling you we're not concerned about that. So the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says ואימא הכי נמי *v'eima hacha nami*, why not actually
say that? That's a good thing to be concerned about. No, אפילו
הכי עדיפא *afilu hacha adeifa*, even if that's a possibility, this is
more important. Why? So have the word יתירה *yeseira* או *o* חסירה
*chaseira*, anyway it's better to make this מום mum *Mum*, why? מדי
אתי לידי גיזה ועבודה *mid'asi lidei gizeh v'avodah*. It protects you from
other things. Meaning it protects you if you leave a בכור bechor
*Bechor* standing around you have to raise it for 20 years till
it gets a מום *Mum*, there's many, many opportunities of misuse. So
I'd rather not be
גוזר *gozer*, accidentally do it after the head emerges because I have
to look at big picture and big picture it makes more sense
to allow you to do this. That is, that's the best way
of dealing with this situation. So what's important from the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* is that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* first of all says, I
give scheming would only allow if you're making things better, okay, not
if you're making them equivalent or worse, we're not going to allow
you to scheme and therefore nowadays it is better to make a
מום *Mum* because that is the much you can't bring it as
a קרבן *Korban* and that just allows us the the issue to
be dealt with much in a much more efficient way. What about
the בכור bechor.
*Bechor* that has a מום *Mum*, the blood's not brought, right? Right,
just. So how is that making it equal if?
Because it can't be brought nowadays, there's no בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash*.
Oh, but when there was a בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash*.
Then you couldn't make a מום *Mum* and he would not allow.
Right, that's what it says, I'm only allowing it nowadays when it
has no option of being brought as a קרבן *Korban*.
Or why didn't they suggest the partnership with a גוי *Goy*?
Oh, so תוספות Tosafos, *Tosafos* says, well because that seems to be...
So that's a good point. Why didn't they suggest what was done
in the time of the ראשונים, sell the ear of the mother
to a non-Jew so it gets you out of it, because that
actually would be bringing it down. It would go out from being
קדושת בכור kedushat bechor to being eaten by a כהן, kohen and
you basically would be taking it away from the כהן, removing its
קדושה, kedusha preventing it from being a בכור. bechor. So that actually
is a bringing down. So the question is okay, so then how
do we do that? So if you take a look at תוספות,
Tosafos right, תוספות Tosafos is always quick to say this. He says
הא עדיפא להו מדאיתיה לידי גיזה ועבודה. Ha adifa lehu mide’atyei lidei
giza va’avoda. At the end of the first line he says והשתא.
ve’hashta.
I'm sorry, not that. Okay. ואומר רבינו
תם, Ve’omer Rabbeinu Tam, middle of the second line he says דהשתא
נהגו עולם למכור קצת מן האם, de’hashta nahagu olam limkor kzat min
ha’em, they would sell a little part of the mother, usually the
ear, to a non-Jew, כדי להפקיע הולד מן הבכורה. kidei lehafki’a havlad
min habechora. וטוב הוא לעשות כן, Ve’tov hu la’asot kein, ובלבד שיקנה
לו קניין חשוב, u’vilvad sheyikne lo kinyan chashuv, you have to make
sure you do a קניין kinyan that works, so money and doing
the right קניין, kinyan, etc.
Anyway, and he says like this.
And the very last two lines from the bottom he says ניחא
לן טפי למכרו לעובדי כוכבים, nicha lan tefei lemochro le’ovdei chochavim, better
to sell to a non-Jew, מלהטיל בו מום קודם יציאת רובו דלא
אתי למיתי להטיל בו מום אחר יציאת הרוב. mil’hatil bo mum kodem
yetzi’at rubo d’lo ati lemeitei le’hatil bo mum achar yetzi’at harov. משום
הכי טוב לנו לעשות
כן. Mishum hachi tov lanu la’asot kein. So תוספות Tosafos basically says
we don't want to play around with making מומים mumim in בכורות.
bechoros. We're going to do it wrong or maybe you won't even
know that it's a מום קבוע, mum kavu’a, he doesn't say that
but that's also a concern. So rather than playing around with making
a מום, which could obviously lead to certain transgressions, we'd rather sell
the ear of the mother. So that's how תוספות Tosafos explains it.
Now of course one wonders if also economic realities aren't a function,
because the owner certainly is much happier to keep the בכור bechor.
himself than to give it to the כהן. But again, it's interesting
that the גמרא Gemara would not have, you know, that would not
have been a legitimate for the גמרא. Gemara That would have been
a scheme to subvert. For the גמרא Gemara is only allowing this
when it's not subverting. So תוספות's Tosafos question is if we sell
the ear, you really are subverting. It's not going to the כהן,
it's not having any קדושה. kedusha And תוספות justifies it because he
says that that protects from the sin of doing the מום in
a wrong way and so on. But again, it does, one does
wonder if economic pressures also played a role and, you know, like
we're coming up to פסח Pesach and talking about selling your חמץ,
chametz, and often we learn, you know, בכור is the model for
those types of schemes, but it's important to note that the גמרא
Gemara has limits to that.
Yeah, there's no בית המקדש, you could have also made it a
שלמים, right? You're not really making it any less because nothing's going
to the...
yeah, but you wouldn't solve anything.
You can't eat a שלמים either. A שלמים you throw the דם
dam on the מזבח and you eat the meat. But you can't
eat a שלמים without a בית המקדש. Oh, you can't. So the
only thing you can eat without a בית המקדש is a בכור.
בכור and מעשר ma’aser are the exception that if they have a
מום they can be eaten without being brought as a קרבן. Everything
else can only be eaten once it's brought as a קרבן. Okay,
so now the גמרא, Gemara let's just take a look, let's wrap,
get to the bottom of the דף. daf. אם נקבה היא תהא
שלמים, Im nekeiva hi tehei shelamim, and said if it's a female
let it be a שלמים. Now why are you saying that? You've
solved your problem by saying if it's a male let it be
an עולה. olah So the גמרא Gemara says, נקבה מי קמיקדשא בבכורה?
Nekeiva mi kamikadsha be’bechora? Who needs, you know, the female wouldn't have
been a בכור, why bother doing this? So if it's under the
rubric of כיצד מערימין, Keitzad ma’arimin, it understands that this is part
of כיצד מערימין, keitzad ma’arimin, how you get around things. So what
are you getting around? So the גמרא Gemara says, no, סיפא אתיא
לבהמה דהקדש. seifa atya le’veheima de’hekdesh. The end is talking about a
בהמה beheima of הקדש. hekdesh. So what's this story? Meaning, the גמרא's
going to explain it in a minute, but basically it means let's
say the mother is, I don't know, an עולה. olah, Okay. And
it has a baby. Now, the child therefore will not be a
בכור because the child remember gets the קדושה kedusha, of the mother
and if the mother has קדושה kedusha so the child won't be
a בכור. It's a totally different scenario. But your concern therefore is
not about getting around בכור. Your concern is you don't want to
bring another עולה. olah, What you would like to do actually is
bring a שלמים. So in that type of a case what you
can do is sanctify it in the womb of the mother. Why
does that work? Isn't it already an עולה? So as we're going
to spell out, no, this assumes that the קדושה, kedusha the derivative
קדושה kedusha that the fetus gets from the mother occurs at the
moment of birth. And therefore in utero you can give a different
קדושה kedusha to prevent it from getting the קדושה kedusha of the
mother. Okay. So the גמרא says now of course, okay, so the
גמרא says like
this... or רש"י Rashi says, I gave an example of an עולה.
רש"י Rashi gives a better example of a חטאת chatas referring back
to the last פרק. perek. If the mother is a חטאת, chatas,
right, עולה wouldn't be... what did I say? עולה's a male. Okay,
yeah, you should have stopped me. Okay.
Okay, so רש"י Rashi says the עולה wouldn't have worked.
So anyway רש"י Rashi says it was a חטאת. chatas. So
that's in context of the last פרק. perek. You want to get
around from it being a ולד חטאת velad chatas and you don't
want it to die. So what do you do to prevent it
from dying? Now we understand why you really want to do something.
You want it to stop dying, so you make it into a
שלמים. Okay. You give it some other קדושה kedusha. so that it
doesn't have derivative קדושה kedusha of the mother.
Yes, but that's lowering it.
So I was wondering about that but first of all, it's not
taking it away from the כהן like the first case. So that's
one factor. The other factor is, no, you're not lowering it if
you're preventing it, maybe in my scenario, which won't happen, but anyway,
but in this case you're not lowering it, you're preventing it from
dying, so you're giving it a higher function. You're allowing it to
be brought as a קרבן. Okay? So right, we're not talking, I
mean technically it's קדושת קדשים קלים kedushas kodshim kalim but practically you're
allowing it to be brought as a קרבן. Okay, so the גמרא
says like this. ילדה שני זכרים, yalda sheni zecharim, now if it's
two males,
so then
אמרי אי בבהמה דהקדש היכא דאקדיש עולה להדר עולה אידך להוי בקדושה
דאמיה. amri ei bebehema dehekesh heicha de’akdish olah lehader olah idach lehavei
bikdusha d’imeih. So the גמרא says like this, the גמרא thinks that
we're still talking
about a what do you call it, about the case we just
got off, that the animal was, has קדושה. kedusha, Okay? So the
גמרא says like this, if the בהמה דהקדש behema dehekesh that it's
a חטאת, chatas, היכא דאקדיש עולה להדר עולה, heicha de’akdish olah lehader
olah, so fine, so if it has two males, so the one
that you made as an עולה, whichever one that is, is an
עולה, but the other one you shouldn't be able to sell, right?
It says the other one is חולין. chullin. Why is the other
one חולין? chullin? אידך להוי בקדושה דאמיה, idach lehavei bikdusha d’imeih, the
other one should have the derivative קדושה kedusha, of the mother. Right,
remember the case of the two? Right? So it says one has
קדושה, kedusha. not the other. But if they're born from a mother
that has קדושה, they should both have
קדושה. גמרא says no, סיפא אתאן לבהמת חולין. seifa asan lebehemas chullin.
When we get back to the case of two, then we're back
to the case of a non-sanctified animal. Okay, so the גמרא will
continue in this vein tomorrow, but basically it says that the scenario
of the female was where you were trying to get it out
from being a ולד חטאת. vlad chatas. But then by the time
we get back to the end of this, we're talking more about
scenarios of it just being a חולין chullin animal and you're trying
to get out of being בכור. And we will continue tomorrow.